Guide to the Eleanor Poorman Hamilton papers, 1959-1999.
Hamilton, Eleanor Poorman papers
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Eleanor Poorman Hamilton papers, 1959-1999.
7836
Hamilton, Eleanor Poorman,
.3
Manuscripts, printed materials.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Collection includes articles by Eleanor Hamilton from weekly columns in Point Reyes Light and manuscripts of unpublished autobiographical material, including "Story of a Happy Marriage", "My Vow, "The Maternal Care Adoption Center" and "The Treasure and Tragedy of Wilhelm Reich".
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Born Eleanor Poorman in Portland in 1909, Hamilton grew up in Oregon. While a college student, she decided to devote her life to improving women's experiences with love and sex. After graduating from the University of Oregon in 1930, she spent a career as an educator and psychologist in New York and California. She helped young women get contraceptives in the 1940s, arranged private, semi-open adoptions long before they became legal, participated in the Kinsey report on Americans' sex lives, and studied the work of Wilhelm Reich. She wrote a sex-and-love column for Modern Bride magazine in the 1960s, published several books (Partners in Love, Sex Before Marriage), and talked about sexuality on television talk shows including Phil Donahue and Johnny Carson. In 1932, she married Albert Edward Hamilton who nicknamed her Ranger. They raised children. After he died in 1969, she moved to California and had two relationships with women. She returned to Oregon in 1995 and died in 2008.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Collection includes articles by Eleanor Hamilton from weekly columns in Point Reyes Light and Modern Bride and manuscripts of unpublished autobiographical material, including "Story of a Happy Marriage", "My Vow, "The Maternal Care Adoption Center" and "The Treasure and Tragedy of Wilhelm Reich".
SUBJECTS
Names:
Hamilton, Eleanor Poorman, 1909-2008.
Titles:
Point Reyes light.
Subjects:
Marriage.; Couples.; Sex.; Contraception.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
CONTAINER LIST
- Photo of Eleanor Hamilton, Undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Autobiographicals, unpublished, Undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  The Story of a Happy Marriage, My Vow, The Maternal Care Adoption Center, The Treasure and Tragedy of Wilhelm Reich
- Typed articles, Undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Point Reyes Light, Living and Loving columns, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Point Reyes Light, Living and Loving columns, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Point Reyes Light, Living and Loving columns, 1990's (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Point Reyes Light, Living and Loving columns, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Point Reyes Light, Living and Loving columns, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Point Reyes Light, Living and Loving columns, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Point Reyes Light, Living and Loving columns, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Point Reyes Light, Living and Loving columns, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Point Reyes Light, Living and Loving columns, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Modern Bride articles, 1959-1963 (Folder 1)
SEPARATED MATERIAL
Books - cataloged individually in the Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections
Hamilton, Eleanor. Partners In Love, 1968 (revised edition, abridged)
Hamilton, Eleanor. Sex Before Marriage, 1969
Hamilton, Eleanor. Sex, with Love, A Guide for Young People, 1978 (inscribed by author to "Dear John...")